Good morning. So today's דף daf is well ט tes but we
started at the bottom of ח עמוד א chet amud aleph about
five lines from the bottom and we're dealing with מוציא שם רע.
motzi shem ra. We just saw the ירושלמי Yerushalmi that gave two
explanations of this debate. Are they debating when the case is against
the woman starts with ממונות mamonot and וקרב v'karav to דיני נפשות
dinei nefashot or the case is against the man where it starts
with both דיני נפשות dinei nefashot and דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot, דיני
נפשות dinei nefashot against the עדים eidim and דיני ממונות dinei mamonot
against the man? So that's two ways the ירושלמי Yerushalmi explained it.
Nice clear way of framing it. Let's see what the בבלי Bavli
says. וחכמים אומרים מוציא שם רע בעשרים ושלושה. vachachamim omrim motzi shem
ra b'esrim v'shlosha. The case of מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra
חכמים hachachamim say is 23 and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's
three. So the גמרא Gemara says וכי יש בו v'chi yesh bo
ח עמוד א chet amud aleph in the בבלי Bavli five lines
from the bottom. וכי יש בו דיני נפשות מאי הוי? v'chi yesh
bo dinei nefashot mai havei? Right, so because חכמים hachachamim said back
it's 23 because there's an element of דיני נפשות dinei nefashot in
it. So it says so what if there's an element of דיני
נפשות dinei nefashot in it? We're dealing with the דיני ממונות dinei
mamonot aspect of it. So אמר עולא בחוששים ללעז מפלגי. amar ulla
bechoshshim l'la'az miflagi. The debate is are you afraid of rumor or
like a bad you know gossip? רבי מאיר סבר אין חוששים ללעז,
Rabbi Meir savar ein choshshim l'la'az, you're not afraid of rumor. רבנן
סברי חוששים ללעז, rabanan savri choshshim l'la'az, you're afraid of rumor. So
what the heck does that mean? So here for once the בבלי
Bavli is a lot more cryptic than the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. I'll tell
you what רש"י Rashi says and then I'll tell you what תוספות
Tosafot says. רש"י Rashi says what it means is it's a case
against the woman you start with three that's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says but חכמים hachachamim say oh but once people start hearing oh
did you hear there's a case against this woman she wasn't a
virgin on her wedding night what what's that about or whatever people
might realize that might lead to witnesses coming forward and actually testifying
that she committed adultery not that she wasn't a woman and then
it could turn into the capital or not that she wasn't a
virgin and then it could turn into the capital case capital crime
and then it would require 23. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
you know no no we're not afraid of that it's a ממונות
mamonot case you start with three and חכמים hachachamim say it could
turn into a דיני נפשות dinei nefashot case that's חוששים ללעז choshshim
l'la'az and therefore it is 23. So why can't you just add
them in the extra? So it's a funny phrase I don't because
well I'll get to that in a second so it's a funny
phrase about חוששים ללעז choshshim l'la'az because it's not a לעז la'az
I mean it's a לעז la'az I guess because they're gossiping about
her but it's really a question about getting the word out and
bringing witnesses. Okay but then it's a simple framing of is it
starts with דיני ממונות dinei mamonot against the woman and are we
concerned that it would evolve into a דיני נפשות dinei nefashot case?
That's the way רש"י Rashi says it. תוספות Tosafot does not like
this at all. First of all he says that's not what the
word לעז la'az means. Second of all תוספות Tosafot says that the
phrase of מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra always refers to the
case against the man not the case against the woman. Does that
sound like something where did we just hear that? In the ירושלמי.
Yerushalmi. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi started with an opinion that it was a
case against the woman and then the pushback in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi
was what are you talking about מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra
means a case against the man it doesn't mean a case against
woman. So תוספות Tosafot has a lot of lot of questions on
רש"י Rashi and therefore
תוספות Tosafot says no no no we are not talking about the
case against women we're talking about the cases against the man. Okay
and therefore רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says three because he pays ממון.
mamon. So what's חכמים's hachachamim חוששים ללעז choshshim l'la'az type of a
concern? So the חוששים ללעז choshshim l'la'az type of a concern תוספות
Tosafot he does a lot of like what do you call it
like somersaults in order to explain this. He תוספות Tosafot wants to
suggest and I don't want to get into this it's complicated I'll
just tell you very quickly that there could be a case against
the man without the עדים eidim being חייב מיתה. chayav misa. How
could there be a case against man without the עדים חייב מיתה?
eidim chayav misa? We always assume only when the עדים eidim are
proven זוממים zomemim is the man does the man have to pay
and get the lashes. So תוספות Tosafot says and this is a
huge חידוש chiddush which תוספות Tosafot acknowledges eventually which is is that
let's say the man brought witnesses that the woman committed adultery and
then other witnesses came and they didn't make them זוממים zomemim but
they contradicted them they gave opposite testimony no no the woman was
with us he couldn't have been the guy you claim she committed
adultery with we saw him somewhere else it's not זוממות zomemut you're
not saying the witnesses were somewhere else it neutralizes the witnesses. So
תוספות Tosafot is making a claim that
even in the case where they would be neutralized the husband would
have to pay the fine and get lashes which is a huge
חידוש chiddush because you don't know the husband is lying in that
case right it's just two against two but that's how תוספות Tosafot
tries to make it parallel to this issue of the woman. It
starts with a דיני ממונות dinei mamonot against the man okay because
his witnesses were neutralized but it could turn into a דיני נפשות
dinei nefashot because the witnesses could become זוממים. zomemim. All right so
it's very very complicated and that חוששים ללעז choshshim l'la'az would be
by the way the לעז la'az for the תוספות Tosafot is and
this answers Michael's point
is and this you could say even according to רש"י Rashi as
well the לעז la'az is not the rumor will get out and
you'll have to add and you know and will turn into דיני
נפשות dinei nefashot case that would be a good thing. The לעז
la'az will be when we have to add will that make the
original judges look bad okay because people will They'd say oh why
did you have to add, must be they weren't competent. Okay so
חוששים ללעז chosheshim l'la'az means well okay maybe we'll turn into a
דיני נפשות dinei nefashos case, let's worry about it then. Why not
find it when that happens we'll just add judges. No, no, no,
the answer is we don't want to do that because חוששים ללעז.
chosheshim l'la'az. It'll look bad to the original judges. And the other
approach will say אין חוששים ללעז. ein chosheshim l'la'az. You know what?
If we have to add, we'll add, we'll worry about it then.
We don't care how it might make the original judges look. Okay,
so that was all very complicated, but what I wanted you to
hear was that תוספות Tosafos takes this... first of all, there's a
question what does חוששים ללעז chosheshim l'la'az mean? Does חוששים ללעז chosheshim
l'la'az mean we're afraid that the word will get out and it'll
turn into a דיני נפשות dinei nefashos case? Or does חוששים ללעז
chosheshim l'la'az mean, okay, it'll turn into a דיני נפשות dinei nefashos
case, but do we have to worry that adding judges will make
the original judges look bad? That's, you know, whatever, those are two
meanings of חוששים ללעז. chosheshim l'la'az. They both, what they both share
is that the question is that the דיני ממונות dinei mammonos case
will turn into a דיני נפשות dinei nefashos case. Okay, and that's
the question, and therefore do we have to start with twenty-three because
that might happen? But the other point is that תוספות Tosafos tries
to turn this into the case against the man, which is exactly
the second opinion in the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. So I want you to
just look at one line if you turn the page, ח עמוד
ב, ches amud beis, at the bottom of this
תוספות, Tosafos, והביא האב עדים והזימום. v'heivi ha'av eidim v'hizimum. תוספות Tosafos
says, so after going trying to work out the whole סוגיא sugya
according to him and according to רש"י, Rashi, at the end he
says the following. He says, ובירושלמי, u'vi'Yerushalmi, you see three lines before
חוששים, chosheshim, three lines before the end of that תוספות, Tosafos, והביא
האב, v'heivi ha'av, on ח עמוד ב, ches amud beis, 8B. He
says, ובירושלמי מצא רשב"א, u'vi'Yerushalmi matza Rashba, that's not the רשב"א Rashba
that we know from the ספרדי Sefardi world, that's
רב שמשון. Rav Shimshon. מצא
רשב"א פלוגתא דאמוראי. matza Rashba plugta d'amora'ei. איכא
דמפרשי פלוגתא לינסובה ika d'mifarshei plugta l'insuva כדמפרש בקונטרס, ki'd'mifaresh b'kuntres, ואיכא
דמפרשי לין קטליה
סלע v'ika d'mifarshei l'ein katlei sela כדמפרש רבנו תם. ki'd'mifaresh Rabbeinu Tam.
Look at that. So the two opinions in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, the
בבלי Bavli is cryptic. Is it about him or is it about
her? And those are the major debate of the ראשונים, Rishonim, how
to read the בבלי. Bavli. And then תוספות Tosafos says guess what,
this debate of the ראשונים Rishonim actually was the same thing that's
being debated in the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. Because what it's pointing to is
the inherent ambiguity in the סוגיא sugya itself. And often you find
this, right? That debates of ראשונים Rishonim
parallel in, you know, like implicit different reads of the text, right?
And those implicit different reads might be reflected in like a בבלי
ירושלמי Bavli-Yerushalmi difference, and here actually two opinions that are explicitly identical.
So the ירושלמי Yerushalmi actually has a very clear framing of this.
In our גמרא Gemara it's less clear. But let's go back to
our גמרא. Gemara. We're going to work with רש"י Rashi just because
he's easier. Okay? And actually that was the first approach of the
ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. So let's go back.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר עולא, amar Ulla, let's pick it
up again, four lines from the bottom. אמר עולא בחוששין ללעז קמיפלגי.
amar Ulla b'chosheshin l'la'az kamipalgi. רבי מאיר סבר אין חוששין ללעז. Rabbi
Meir savar ein chosheshin l'la'az. So you start with a בית דין
beis din of three because it's against the woman. We're going to
read it that way. And רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says I'm not
afraid that that will turn into twenty-three. Okay, and if it does
turn into twenty-three you can just add judges and I'm not afraid
it'll make the earlier judges look bad. ורבנן סברי חוששין ללעז. v'rabbanan
savrei chosheshin l'la'az. No, we are afraid it'll turn into twenty-three and
we don't want to add the judges then, it'll make the original
judges look bad. So we're going to start with twenty-three right now.
That's what אמר עולא amar Ulla says. רבא Rava's. אמר... what? Okay.
רבא Rava אמר I gave you both readings of the word לעז.
la'az. רבא אמר כולי עלמא ללעז לא חיישינן. Rava amar kuli alma
l'la'az lo chashinan. Everybody agrees we're not afraid of a three turning
into a case of
twenty-three. Okay. והכא בכבודן של ראשונים קמיפלגי. v'hacha b'chivodan shel rishonim kamipalgi.
The debate is are you concerned about the honor
of the first judges. That sounds like חוששים ללעז. chosheshim l'la'az. But
no, no, no, he's going to explain it the following way.
והכא במאי עסקינן כגון דאיכניסו בי עשרין ותלתא. v'hacha b'mai askinan k'gon
d'ichnisu bei esrin v'tlasa. It's the opposite. It's not that you're going
to add judges but that you're going to take away judges. So
it's like לעז la'az but it's almost like, you know, a different
variation of it. Okay. You started with a בית דין beis din
of twenty-three. The guy said I have witnesses that my wife committed
adultery and he got together a court of twenty-three. Okay,
למידן דיני נפשות. l'meidan dinei nefashos. ואזדו. v'izdu. They scattered. He said,
'Ach, you know, the בית דין, beis din, meaning the בית דין
beis din broke up because it was clear like he wasn't going
to be able to prove that his wife committed adultery. Okay, ואמר
להו דיינו לי מיהא דיני ממונות. v'amar lehu dainu li miha dinei
mammonos. Wait, don't go running away. Fine, I can't prove she committed
adultery but let me just make a proof that she deserves to
lose her כתובה. kesuvah. Okay, and therefore the debate is, it's like
the opposite of from three to twenty-three, it's from twenty-three to three.
So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you let twenty of them go
home, okay, take care of, you know, go to their wives and
kids, and three stay along around to do דיני ממונות. dinei mammonos.
And the חכמים chachamim say since we started with twenty-three we're going
to keep the twenty-three. It would not be, it would be a
concern of the honor of the judges if you sort of dismiss
twenty of them. Wow. Okay, I don't know. Okay, I like עולא's
Ulla's read better than רבא's. Rava Anyway, מיתיבי, meisivei, the גמרא Gemara
asks you. We have a ברייתא braisa that says the
following: וחכמים אומרים תבעו ממון... v'chachamim omrim tavo'u mammon... three, תובעו נפשות
בעשרים ושלושה. tovu nefashos be-esrim ushlosha. Now this sounds like a רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir position, but חכמים Chachamim say look, we'll agree to
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir that if it was only a דיני ממונות
dinei mamonos case it would be three, but if it was basically
a דיני נפשות dinei nefashos case it was a capital case it
would be 23. So okay, but that sounds exactly like what רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir said. So what does that mean? So בשלמא bishlama
לרבא le-Rava or לרבה, or le-Rabbah, there's a question whether it was
רבא Rava or רבה, Rabbah, we get: תובעו ממון תחילה, tovu mamon
techila, if the whole case began with a דיני ממונות dinei mamonos
case, then everybody agrees, בשלושה. bishlosha. תובעו נפשות תחילה, tovu nefashos techila,
if it began with a capital case, but then it turned out
that he couldn't produce the witnesses and you were left with three
and it was left with a דיני ממונות dinei mamonos case, then
תובעו נפשות תחילה אפילו ממון, tovu nefashos techila afilu mamon, then even
if you're left with a monetary case, בעשרים ושלושה be-esrim ushlosha you
keep it as 23. That works very nicely, cause there חכמים Chachamim
are saying if you started with a monetary case we agree to
you, but if it started with a capital case you're going to
leave it at 23. So say אלא ella לעולא le-Ulla קשיא, kashya,
but for עולא Ulla it's difficult because עולא Ulla says the case
is you started with a monetary case, רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says
three and the חכמים Chachamim say 23 because they're afraid that the
monetary is going to turn into a דיני נפשות dinei nefashos case.
So how do you read here that the חכמים Chachamim seem to
agree to רבי מאיר? Rebbi Meir? So אמר רבא, amar Rava, so
רבא said: אני ואריה שבחבורה, ani ve-arya she-bachabura, me and the lion
in our group, who's the lion? תרגימנא, Targemina, we've explained this ברייתא
braisa to be consistent with עולא. Ulla. ומאן הוא, u-man hu, who
is this lion? רבי חייא בר אבא. Rebbi Chiya bar Abba. Okay.
Now here's how we're going to explain this ברייתא braisa to work
for עולא, Ulla, because עולא Ulla seems to say that when you
start with a ממונות mamonos case that's the debate, three or 23.
So why are the rabbis agreeing when you start with ממונות mamonos
it's three? So הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha be-mai askinan, what are we
talking about? שהביא הבעל עדים שזינתה והביא האב עדים והזימום. she-heivi ha-ba'al
eidim she-zinta ve-heivi ha-av eidim ve-hizimum. Okay. So the husband brought עדים
eidim that she committed adultery and
the father brought עדים eidim to prove that they were זוממים, zomemim,
meaning what we're now doing is we're flipping it from the case
against the woman to the case against the man. His witnesses are
proven to be עדים זוממים eidim zomemim והזימום עדי הבעל. ve-hizimum eidim
ha-ba'al. So now when we're dealing with the case against the man,
בא לגבות ממון מבעל בשלושה, ba likvos mamon mi-ba'al bishlosha, when we're
coming to go ahead and have the case against the woman, the
man, excuse me, and get the money, that's three. Okay, cause the
man can never turn into a דיני נפשות dinei nefashos case, meaning
the עדים eidim will get killed, but the man is always going
to remain a דיני ממונות dinei mamonos case. So in this case,
when you're coming to have the case against the man, it's going
to, we'll admit it's three.
ובמקום נפשות בעשרים ושלושה, u-ve-makom nefashos be-esrim ushlosha, but in a case
of דיני נפשות dinei nefashos 23. What does that mean? Presumably it
means the עדים eidim are 23, that would be the easy way
to say. Okay, or it could mean but it's the case where
it were to be against the woman, so the woman could turn
into a דיני נפשות dinei nefashos case, we're always going to demand
23. But basically what this is doing is this is doing exactly
what we saw in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, except now that we saw
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi it reads a lot better. We started by saying
the case was against the woman, that's one way of framing the
debate. Now we're saying oh, but if it's the case against the
man, the חכמים Chachamim who say when the case is against the
woman it's always 23 because the woman herself could be put to
death if it turned into a דיני נפשות dinei nefashos case, that's
מקום נפשות makom nefashos 23, there they're going to say you always
start with 23. But when the case is against the man, he,
even though the עדים eidim are going to get put to death,
he's always never going to be more than three. So that's what
they're saying. If it's against the man, we'll say three. Okay, but
if it's against the woman and it could turn into a דיני
נפשות dinei nefashos case, that'll be 23. So just like the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi switched from those two cases, two different ways of understanding which
one would more demand starting with 23. You could say the woman
more demands 23, which is what we're saying now, because she could
always turn into דיני נפשות. dinei nefashos. The man will never be
דיני נפשות, dinei nefashos, he's always three. Or you could say the
reverse, in the man's case there's always somebody getting put to death,
so everybody's going to need 23.
The issue of זוממים zomemim would be resolved in the same trial,
or they wouldn't have a separate trial?
Yeah, so that seems to be to some degree what we're discussing.
You know, the general sense you get is that it's the same
trial. And here though the question is though you might split it
off though because here oh, זוממים zomemim you go to your בית
דין beis din of 23, and the man now is going to
deal with him as a separate type of a case. You know,
but it would be the same trial that they were in the
process of trying to get her put to death. The issues are
the same. Yeah, exactly. Okay. Yeah.
If she's not a virgin she doesn't get death, right? It's only
if she did adultery after she's married.
Correct. After betrothal. There's two stages, remember, there's קידושין kiddushin and נישואין.
nisu'in. On the wedding night after they are finally having sex, he
finds out she's not a virgin, but she's been married to him
for the last year let's say. So the question is did she
have that act of sex in the last year? for committed adultery
and then she would get death.
But if she had it before the betrothal then right it's just
a כתובה. ketubah. Right.
After their marriage sometimes her husband has this jealousy and they go
to the סוטה Sotah situation.
Yeah that's different.
That's not adultery right?
That's just well he suspects adultery.
No I'm sorry I mean that's not a death sentence it's just
according to the ritual and if she dies she dies.
Right right. But if witnesses come and prove she committed adultery she
would get death. Even then? Sure that's just a case of adultery
at any. Okay
yeah yeah.
So it's obvious that the אבי הבת avi habat is her father
right?
Yeah yeah yeah. But of course she is here a non-subject to
the proceeding she's the you know it's all between the men here
is the way it's sort of framed in the תורה. Torah.
It doesn't even mention the woman in this.
All right so anyway so it says okay אביי
אמר. Abaye amar.
So anyway so now we've got two reads of that right whether
the חכמים Chachamim would switch their position or would agree that you
could start with three when it's about the man not about the
woman. But now we've had two reads רבא and עולא Ulla that
it was against the woman. Okay and the question is do we
start with three or do we start with twenty-three when it's against
the woman? And against the man might be a different story. Now
now you could just stop here. We've laid out the basic approaches
to this debate. This is where the ירושלמי Yerushalmi stops. But here's
also where you see that the בבלי Bavli
you know sort of you know a type of a normal mode
of the בבלי Bavli which is you have a like a cryptic
debate you have a debate in the משנה Mishnah it's not clear
what. Let's use this as an opportunity to suggest a million possibilities
about what they might be debating about and drawing on other types
of debates that we're aware of. Okay so what now we're going
to see is what I would call wild reads of the משנה
Mishnah which are completely absent from the ירושלמי Yerushalmi but because it's
not clear what חכמים Chachamim and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir are debating
it allows us to read into it other types of debates. So
let's take a look. And it's clear it's the later אמוראים Amoraim
who are suggesting this. אביי אמר דכולי עלמא חיישינן ללעז Abaye amar
dechulei alma chaishinan lela'az everybody might agree we're concerned about לעז la'az
that three will turn into
twenty-three ומשום כבודן של ראשונים umishum kvodan shel rishonim and this issue
about you know if a בית דין Beit Din disperses is it
going to be respectful for the original judges? Forget those issues. הכא
במאי עסקינן Hacha b'mai askinan what are we talking about? כגון דאטרו
בה סתם Kegon d'atru bah stam it's a case against her like
we've been assuming and
but they gave her התראה hatra'ah and they didn't tell her what
type of death penalty she would be deserving. They just said if
you commit adultery you're חייב מיתה chayav mitah they didn't tell her
which
מיתה. mitah. והאי תנא הוא דתניא ושאר כל חייבי מיתות שבתורה Ve'hai
tanna hu d'tanya v'sha'ar kol chayavei mitot shebaTorah all other meaning the
discussion there in the תוספתא Tosefta was about the מסית ומדיח mesit
u'madiach the person who seduces to idolatry and there you hide the
witnesses you only give a very subtle warning right you try to
so it's a little bit of entrapment with that person. Not totally
but anyway. But it says that's by the מסית ומדיח mesit u'madiach
but ושאר כל חייבי מיתות שבתורה v'sha'ar kol chayavei mitot shebaTorah but
all other death penalties in the תורה Torah אין ממיתים אותם אלא
בעדה ein mamitim otam ela b'edah it
requires a full community meaning a בית דין Beit Din of twenty-three
ועדים v'edim and witnesses that are not hidden but are obvious והתראה
v'hatra'ah and explicit warning ועד שיודיעוהו שהוא חייב מיתה בבית דין v'ad
sheyodi'uhu shehu chayav mitah b'veit din and it's you have to know
not just it's forbidden to do it but it's deserving of a
death in the court. It has to be התראה hatra'ah with a
clear sense of the punishment. רבי יהודה אומר עד שיודיעוהו באיזו מיתה
הוא נהרג Rabbi Yehuda omer ad sheyodi'uhu b'eizo mitah hu neherag it's
not enough to tell them that you're חייב מיתה chayav mitah it
has to be which one you're deserving of. So what does that
mean? So it means now רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says three because
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says oh this'll never turn into a דיני
נפשות dinei nefashot case because the witnesses didn't tell her which specific
you know death penalty she would be it would be warranting. And
the חכמים Chachamim say no no no you have to start with
twenty-three because it is going to be a דיני נפשות dinei nefashot
case because even without being specific about the death penalty you could
put you know the person could be חייב מיתה. chayav mitah. So
of course has nothing to do right with what it seems like
they're really debating. Let's just import some other debate. רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says they'll never be death penalty because they did the warning
incorrectly and the חכמים Chachamim say twenty-three because there can be a
death penalty. Now we're going to have another another series of things
like this. Okay. רב פפא
אמר הכא באשה חבירה עסקינן Rav Pappa amar hacha b'ishah chaverah askinan
we're talking about a woman who is a חבירה chaverah she's like
a from you know she's like a learned woman.
וקמיפלגי בפלוגתא דרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה ורבנן V'kamiflegi b'plugta d'Rabbi Yosi b'Rabbi
Yehuda v'Rabbanan and the case is they didn't give her warning and
it's the following debate. דתניא רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר חבר אין
צריך התראה Detanya Rabbi Yosi b'Rabbi Yehuda omer chaver ein tzarich hatra'ah
if somebody is like a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and knows the
הלכה halachah then you don't have to give them warning because the
whole purpose of warning is to know that the person is aware
of the gravity of their sin. And if somebody is knowledgeable and
clearly aware sort of like saying like if somebody is a criminal
lawyer you don't have to warn them because they they obviously know
what crime they're committing. Okay. לפי שלא ניתנה התראה אלא להבחין בין
שוגג למזיד Lefi shelo nitna hatra'ah ela l'havchin bein shogeg l'mezid the
whole purpose of התראה hatra'ah is to know if the person is
intentional or unintentional. And therefore you don't need it and the other
and the answer and the other answer is no, you always need
it. Why would you always need it? Well, for the one part,
how do you exactly identify whether somebody does know something or not
know something? People can forget in the moment of passion, but the
other explanation also is it's not just the purpose of התראה hatra'ah
is not just to determine intentionality, the purpose of התראה hatra'ah is
to make the sin one of defiance. You know, if I you
tell me I'm not allowed to do it and what my punishment
will be and I say אף על פי כן, af al pi
chen, I'm not just sinning, there's a certain element of like rejecting
and defying. The other way to explain it even taking that one
step further is the גמרא Gemara later in סנהדרין Sanhedrin we're going
to see this coming up says עד שיתיר עצמו לאותה מיתה ad
she'yatir atzmo le'otah mitah that there's always this question about what gives
the court the right to use violence against another person and to
take another person's life. But if the person says I know I
am going to be חייב מיתה chayav mitah and I accept that
upon me in the performance of this sin, then you basically have
given the court license now to take your life. Okay, so it's
part of what allows them to execute somebody. So anyway, there's different
explanations of התראה hatra'ah which are not just to determine intentionality. What
the גמרא Gemara will get to it later, I'd have to find
the דף, daf, but later in סנהדרין Sanhedrin I think נ-something nun
whatever I'll find it anyway. Okay, so anyway so this that's a
debate. Is the woman going to be חייב מיתה chayav mitah or
not? She didn't get התראה hatra'ah but she was a תלמידת חכם
talmidat chacham so therefore or חכמה chachama anyway and therefore
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says she'll never get מיתה mitah you did
the warning you didn't do warning three and the חכמים Chachamim say
she get מיתה mitah we don't need warning twenty-three. Okay רב אשי
אמר כגון Rav Ashi amar kegon and we're going to have a
series of these דאסרו בה במלקות ולא אסרו בה בקטלה. de'asru bah
bemalkut velo asru bah bekatalah. They warned her with מלקות malkut they
said hey if you commit adultery you'll get lashes. They gave her
the wrong warning not death penalty. So she's never going to get
the death penalty. Everybody would agree if she said lashes and not
death and not the death penalty you can't give the person the
death penalty. Ah so the question is she's חייב מלקות. chayav malkut.
But does מלקות malkut get three or
twenty-three? וכמיפלגי בפלוגתא דרבי ישמעאל ורבנן vekamipeligi bepelugta deRabbi Yishmael veRabbanan the
debate is what the debate we have later in our משנה Mishnah
דתנן מלקות בשלושה משום רבי ישמעאל אמרו בעשרים ושלושה. detnan malkut bishloshah
mishum Rabbi Yishmael amru be'esrim ushloshah. Okay so that's a way of
explaining the debate. It's only a case of מלקות malkut so does
that get three or twenty-three. It doesn't fit the language of the
משנה Mishnah at all because the משנה Mishnah said the חכמים Chachamim
said you get twenty-three because there's דיני נפשות. dinei nefashot. According to
this it has nothing to do with דיני נפשות dinei nefashot you
get twenty-three because מלקות malkut is twenty-three. Anyway I don't understand why
they didn't just say that therefore they're debating the case of the
man. The man does get מלקות malkut he pays a hundred shekel
and gets מלקות. malkut. So according to this just say they're debating
the man not the woman. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says three
because מלקות malkut is three and the חכמים Chachamim say twenty-three. This
is a very weak read. Anyway moving on רבינא אמר כגון שנמצא
אחד מן העדים קרוב ופסול. Ravina amar kegon shenimza echad min ha'edim
karov upasul. Oh here's the issue. Can it is she going to
be חייב מיתה chayav mitah and twenty-three or not and get three
and what's the issue? You had three witnesses that say she committed
adultery and one of them is a relative. So does that mean
that you can still have the other two find her guilty and
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says no she's never going to be it's
not found guilty with this everybody gets thrown out it's only going
to be a monetary issue three and the חכמים Chachamim say we
could kill find her guilty still find her guilty for committing adultery
and twenty-three. So what's this issue about קרוב ופסול? karov upasul? וכמיפלגי
בפלוגתא דרבי יוסי ורבי vekamipeligi bepelugta deRabbi Yosi veRebbi the debate of
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi and רבי Rebbi אליבא דרבי עקיבא aliba deRabbi
Akiva who debate within רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva position. What does this
mean? דתנן רבי עקיבא אומר לא בשלישי אלא להחמיר עליו לעשות דינו
כיוצא באלו. detnan Rabbi Akiva omer lo bashlishi ela lehachmir alav la'asot
dino kiyotze be'elu. He says when the תורה Torah says על פי
שנים עדים או שלשה עדים יומת המת al pi shenayim edim o
sheloshah edim yumat hamet why does it have to say three people?
If it says you get two witnesses can get you killed, three
can also get you killed. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says it
is coming to be strict on the third guy and to say
let's say you had three witnesses that found ראובן שמעון ולוי Reuven
Shimon and Levi and they testified they're not brothers they testified in
that order okay and then they were all proven to be זוממין.
zomemin. And so are you going to kill לוי? Levi? Because לוי
Levi could say you know what even if I didn't show up
to court ראובן ושמעון Reuven and Shimon already were going to get
the person חייב מיתה. chayav mitah. My testimony didn't add anything. So
since my testimony didn't make this person more חייב מיתה chayav mitah
I should not get the punishment of עדים זוממין edim zomemin right
what I did was not consequential. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
that's why it says two or three that the third one is
going to get the same punishment as the first two even though
he came third and it wasn't really necessary.
And the litigant brought a third
no you only need two witnesses to
make them זוממין zomemin no you brought a third in order to
strengthen the
case presumably yeah לא בשלישי אלא להחמיר עליו לעשות דינו כיוצא באלו
lo bashlishi ela lehachmir alav la'asot
dino kiyotze be'elu
that he has the same punishment as the first two if there's
זוממין. zomemin. If the תורה Torah therefore punished the נטפל לעוברי עבירה
כעוברי עבירה nitpal le'ovrei averah ke'ovrei averah and if the תורה Torah
therefore punished... One who sort of appends himself is a tag-on to
the sinner.
For real, right.
But he tagged on to them. Somebody who's tagging himself on in
a peripheral way to the sinners, and he's treated like the principal
sinners themselves, okay? So קל וחומר שישלם שכר נטפל לעושי מצווה כעושי
מצווה. Kal v'chomer she-ishalem sechar nitpal l'osei mitzvah k'osei mitzvah.
So how much more so if you have a group of people,
I don't know, they're all going on Shabbos to do ביקור חולים.
Bikur Cholim. In terms of, oh, I'll tag along,
okay? So we had twenty people without you, you're not really adding
too much, but nevertheless, you're going to get the same reward as
the principal actors. Okay, that was a nice little דרש. drash. But
anyway, but now we're getting to our point. Here's another reason two
and three are linked. ומה שניים, U'mah shnayim, in the same way
if you have only two witnesses, נמצא אחד מהם קרוב או פסול
עדותן בטלה, nimtza echad meihem karov o pasul eidusam bateilah, if one
of them is invalid, everything gets thrown out because then you're only
left with one. אף שלושה נמצא אחד מהם קרוב או פסול עדותן
בטלה. Af shlosha nimtza echad meihem karov o pasul eidusam bateilah. If
three, one of them is invalid, they all get thrown out. ומנין
שאפילו מאה, U'minayin she-afilu meiah, how do I know if you have
a hundred and one of them is invalid, they all get thrown
out? תלמוד לומר עדים. Talmud lomar eidim.
Witnesses, they're all treated as one unit. Now that we know the
principle of נמצא אחד מהם קרוב או פסול.
nimtza echad meihem karov
o pasul. But so what's the debate? Everybody should say all the
witnesses get thrown out. But the debate is what is the scope
of what Rabbi Akiva said? Is it always true or does it
require some other parameters? And here we have a debate. אמר רבי
יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yose, says Rabbi Yose. במה דברים אמורים, B'meh devarim
amurim, when is it true that you throw them all out? בדיני
נפשות, B'dinei nefashos, if it's a capital crime.
אבל בדיני ממונות תתקיים עדות בשאר, Aval b'dinei mammonos tiska-yeim eidus b'sha'ar,
but if it's a monetary crime, then just keep the kosher witnesses.
They're not all treated as one big unit, and keep the kosher
ones and those will still be valid even if some of them
are invalid. That's
Rabbi Yose. רבי, Rabbi, Rabbi says a different distinction. אחד דיני ממונות
ואחד דיני נפשות, Echad dinei mammonos v'echad dinei nefashos, even by דיני
ממונות, dinei mammonos, if one is invalid you'll throw them all out.
However, in which case? ואימתי, V'eimasai, when is that true? בזמן שהתרו
בהן. bizman she-hisru bahen.
If the other witnesses show their active participation by giving התראה, hasra-ah,
warning. Okay, now of course the question is how is התראה hasra-ah
relevant by דיני ממונות? dinei mammonos? תוספות Tosafot tries to figure that
in. But you could have by דיני ממונות dinei mammonos everybody as
a unit or דיני נפשות, dinei nefashos, but there's ways even in
דיני נפשות dinei nefashos that extra people won't be considered part of
the witnesses. If it wasn't obvious that they were there to testify.
One of the ways to make it obvious that you're there to
testify is that you actively warn the person, at least in a
דיני נפשות dinei nefashos case. Okay, אבל בזמן שלא התרו בהן, Aval
bizman she-lo hisru bahen, but if it wasn't warning. מה יעשו שני
אחים בתוך אחד שהרג את הנפש. Mah ya'asu shnei achim b'soch echad
she-harag es hanefesh.
So what happened, you have Reuven and Shimon, brothers, going down the
street with Mordechai and they see a murder committed. So all of
a sudden you can't go ahead and just take the two kosher
witnesses? נמצא אחד מהם קרוב או פסול. Nimtza echad meihem karov o
pasul. So Rabbi makes a very logical point. נמצא אחד מהם קרוב
או פסול Nimtza echad meihem karov o pasul is not going to
happen unless there's something that identifies everybody as a witness. Just passive
seeing of it would not make you into a witness. Okay, so
one way is to say it only applies to דיני נפשות. dinei
nefashos. Rabbi is saying it applies to both but only if you're
somehow actively a witness. Now this leads to תוספות Tosafot asking besides
the question of how does that happen by דיני ממונות, dinei mammonos,
this leads to תוספות Tosafot raising the important question about how come
every wedding isn't פסול pasul because there's always relatives in the audience?
Okay, so I just have to read you one line of this
very large תוספות Tosafot on ט עמוד א, Tes amud aleph, if
you take a look.
That's why you do ייחוד yichud eidim.
But according, but that's not in the גמרא Gemara anywhere and according
to a number of פוסקים, poskim, ייחוד yichud eidim doesn't help, doesn't
do anything, right? So look at this תוספות. Tosafot. בזמן שהתרו בהן.
Bizman she-hisru bahen. תוספות Tosafot says, this is on ט עמוד א.
Tes amud aleph. מפרש בפרק קמא דמכות. Mefaresh b'perek kama d'makkos. הכי
אמרינן להו. Hachi amrinan lehu. לאסהודי אתיתו או למיחזי אתיתו. L'as-hodei asisu
o l'michzei asisu. Did you come to testify or did you just
come to watch? אי אמרו לאסהודי אתינו נמצא אחד מהם קרוב או
פסול עדותן בטלה. Ei amru l'as-hodei asinu nimtza echad meihem karov o
pasul eidusam bateilah. If they said we're coming to testify, so it's
not just about giving warning, there's other ways to make yourself an
active witness. Then you invalidate all the rest. ואי אמרו למיחזי אתינו,
V'ei amru l'michzei asinu, and if they said we're just coming to
watch. So in that case מה יעשו שני אחים. mah ya'asu shnei
achim. Okay. ונירא לרי, V'nira l'Ri, now it seems to the Ri.
דמשום שנתכוונו להעיד, de-mishum she-nis-kavnu l'ha-id, even that's not enough, just intending
to bear witness. לא אמרינן נמצא אחד מהם קרוב או פסול עדותן
בטלה. lo amrinan nimtza echad meihem karov o pasul eidusam bateilah. That
would not be enough to invalidate everybody. Why? אלא שהולכין ומעידין כולם
בבית דין. Ela she-holchin u'me-idin kulam b'Beis Din. You need them not
just to witness it, the event, with intent to serve as a
witness, you need them to show up to בית דין Beis Din
with the intent to be a witness. אבל משום ראייה לחודיה שנתכוונו
להעיד לא. Aval mishum re-iyah l'chudei she-nis-kavnu l'ha-id lo. But just seeing
something even if you're doing it with the intent to be a
witness is not enough to invalidate. דאי לא תימא הכי D'ei lo
teima hachi כל גיטין kol gittin כשנותנים אותם בפני קרובים או פסולים
keshenosnim osam bifnei krovim o psulim יהיו פסולים אם נתכוון האחד. yihyu
psulim im nis-kavein ha-echad. Okay, any גט get that there's a relative
there, if they're intending to be a witness they should invalidate and
he doesn't, I don't know, he doesn't mention the wedding. just the
גיטין. gittin. But anyway, then he goes on. So this becomes this
big issue of what do you need to label yourself as a
witness? רבי Rebbe says warning, but warning only works in capital crimes.
It doesn't work in דיני ממונות, dinei mamonos, it doesn't work in
קידושין, kiddushin, it doesn't work in גיטין. gittin. I mean, I guess
you can make a joke about it working in קידושין; kiddushin; people
need
התראה. hasra'ah. Okay, know what you're getting into, but anyway, okay. But
anyway, but so maybe you need intent. But is it enough to
intend to see at the time or do you actually have to
show up to בית דין? beis din? Like how exactly do you
get labeled as a witness so נמצא אחד קרוב או פסול nimtza
echad karov o pasul would be relevant? So that's a very big
question in the ראשונים. Rishonim. But anyway, let's say how does this
fit in our משנה? mishnah? The way it fits in our משנה
mishnah is the following: there was three witnesses.
Okay, so one of them was פסול. pasul. So רבי מאיר Rebbe
Meir says, "Oh, so therefore it's דיני ממונות dinei mamonos because like
the רבי יוסי's Rebbe Yossi position, you can still use the two
כשר kasher ones for דיני ממונות, dinei mamonos, so you'll have a
case of three." It's a דיני ממונות dinei mamonos against the woman,
but she's never going to be
חייב
מיתה chayav misa because it invalidates all of them to serve in
a capital crime. What would the חכמים Chachamim hold, who say twenty-three?
They would hold like רבי. Rebbe. They would say that invalid witness
did not invalidate the group for דיני נפשות dinei nefashos because the
invalid witness didn't warn. And since the invalid witness didn't warn or
didn't intend to be a witness, then the remaining two can still
serve as דיני נפשות. dinei nefashos. Okay, so now we've got the
debate to be: one of them was invalid. רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir
says it's only a דיני ממונות dinei mamonos case, you're allowed to
keep the two good ones for דיני ממונות, dinei mamonos, but it's
not a דיני נפשות. dinei nefashos. And the חכמים Chachamim say it's
a דיני נפשות dinei nefashos because you can throw out the one
witness who didn't do the warning and wasn't an active witness and
you can throw that one out and still retain the two for
דיני נפשות. dinei nefashos. Rabbi Rosen?
Yes. So, but in that case the one that didn't give the
warning that gets thrown out and then you keep two valid witnesses,
that one has to be one of the two קרובים krovim to
each other.
Yeah, yes, it's the one that invalidates and you're left with two
good ones.
And there's one of those two אחים. achim.
Correct. Correct. Okay. ואי בעית אימא, V'ee ba'is eima, if you want
you could say, so here's another yet another way of explaining the
debate of רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir and the חכמים. Chachamim. All of
these are of course totally not פשט. pshat. Okay, the פשט pshat
were the ones we had at the beginning which was paralleling what
we had in the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. ואי בעית אימא, V'ee ba'is eima,
if you want you could say, שהתרו באחרים ולא התרו בעדים. she'hisru
ba'acherim v'lo hisru ba'edim.
Here's the issue: can it be a דיני נפשות dinei nefashos case
that you had other people who weren't the witnesses who gave the
warning: "Hey, don't commit adultery, you'll be חייב מיתה." chayav misa. ובמפלגי
בפלוגתא דרבי יוסי ורבנן, U'v'miflagi biflugta d'Rebbe Yossi v'rabanan,
it's the debate of רבי יוסי Rebbe Yossi and the רבנן rabanan
דתנן. d'isnan. רבי יוסי אומר לעולם אינו נהרג עד שיהיו שני עדים
מתרין בו. Rebbe Yossi omer l'olam eino neherag ad she'yiyu shenei edim
masrin bo. You need the witnesses themselves to deliver the warning, שנאמר
על פי שני עדים, she'ne'emar al pi shenei edim, by the mouth
of them.
So that's a debate. רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir says the warning was
done incorrectly, only ממונות mamonos three, and the חכמים Chachamim say the
warning was fine, it could be נפשות nefashos twenty-three. ואי בעית אימא,
V'ee ba'is eima, if you want you could say, דאכחשי בבדיקות ולא
אכחשי בחקירות. d'iskachashi b'vedikos v'lo iskachashi b'chakirosh.
That the witnesses who were coming to make this woman חייב מיתה
chayav misa committing adultery, they were shown to be- they contradicted one
another
in the בדיקות, bedikos, which means like in the details of exactly
what happened, but not in the חקירות. chakiros. The חקירות chakiros is
when it happened. The when and where it happened is seen as
central. And if you get any of those things because that's what
can turn you into an עד זומם ed zomem because we could
say you couldn't have seen it at that time and place because
you were with us. So if there's any contradiction in the where
and the when, the testimony is thrown out. But what if the
contradiction is in the what? You know, and some minor detail of
the what? Is that enough to throw them out? Okay. ובמפלגי בפלוגתא
דבן זכאי ורבנן. U'v'miflagi biflugta d'Ben Zakkai v'rabanan. The debate of בן
זכאי Ben Zakkai and the רבנן. rabanan. דתנן, D'isnan, מעשה ובדק בן
זכאי בעוקצי תאנים. ma'aseh u'vadak Ben Zakkai b'uktzei te'einim. בן זכאי Ben
Zakkai would ask them,
"So you say the crime happened under a fig tree, tell me,
were the stems of the figs, were they pointed north or were
they pointed south? Were they sharp or were they smooth?" And he
would ask all these נודניק nudnik questions until he could get them
to trip up, because the idea you try to avoid דיני נפשות.
dinei nefashos. So the point is, is that enough to throw them
out? So בן זכאי Ben Zakkai says yes, the חכמים Chachamim say
no. So that's what happened. So רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir would say-
רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir says yes, you throw them out, they're not
good for דיני נפשות, dinei nefashos, it's only a דיני ממונות dinei
mamonos case. And the חכמים Chachamim say no, even though they contradicted
in those small points, they're still legitimate witnesses and it's a דיני
נפשות dinei nefashos case. Okay! So that was about ten different reads
of the משנה, mishnah, of which eight of them were really totally
imported from elsewhere. Okay, but the real debates are how much are
we either concerned that the case against the woman starts with דיני
ממונות, dinei mamonos, will evolve to דיני נפשות, dinei nefashos, so therefore
should we start it with three or start it with twenty-three? Or
the other way of looking at it, is against the husband. Against
him it's a דיני ממונות, dinei mamonos, but against his witnesses it's
a דיני נפשות, dinei nefashos, and therefore how much does that mean
we're going to do a case of
three?
Yes, what would you say? What do you think about this though
from the point of view of developing legal theory? So the פשט
pshat or not פשט pshat framework is limiting. The Bavli's agenda for
these pages is an opportunity to expand.
Right, exactly. That is completely true. The Bavli is much more interested
in exploring ideas than in always getting פשט pshat of a text.
100%. Let's just read one more section here. Okay, אמר רב יוסף,
Amar Rav Yosef, הביא בעל עדים שהזנתה והביא האב עדים והזימום לעדי
הבעל. hevi ba'al eidim she'zinta ve'hevi ha'av eidim ve'hizimum le'eidei haba'al. Classic
case of מוציא שם רע. motzi shem ra. He brought witnesses she
committed adultery, the father brought witnesses that his witnesses were lying, were
זוממים. zomemim. So now his witnesses are חייב מיתה. chayav misa. So
the point
is... והזימום לעדי הבעל, ve'hizimum le'eidei haba'al, עדי הבעל נהרגין. eidei haba'al
neheragin. So the husband's witnesses are put to death. They were trying
to kill her. ואין משלמין ממון. ve'ein meshalmin mammon. Even though their
testimony would have also made her lose her כתובה, kesubah, you don't
do both of them. Rashi says it's like a קים ליה. kim
lei. Okay, you punish them, they're חייב מיתה chayav misa for trying
to get her killed, okay, but even though it would have also
made her lose her כתובה, kesubah, they don't also have to pay
her, they don't also pay the
כתובה. kesubah. חזר והביא הבעל עדים והזימום לעדי האב. Chazar ve'hevi haba'al
eidim ve'hizimum le'eidei ha'av. Now let's say it turned around yet again.
Okay, so now the husband brought witnesses that the father's witnesses that
made his first group זוממים zomemim were the liars. So do you
sort of get this? So now it's the husband's witness... so it's
now it's the father's witnesses who were lying and trying to get
true witnesses killed.
עדי אב נהרגין. eidei av neheragin. The father's witnesses are killed because
they were trying to get the husband's legitimate witnesses falsely accused and
killed.
ומשלמין ממון. u'meshalmin mammon. They also pay money. Who do they pay
money to? The husband. Because when the father brought witnesses, what was
the consequences of the father's witnesses? That the husband's witnesses would get
killed and that the husband would pay 100 שקל. shekel. That's your
classic מוציא שם רע. motzi shem ra. Okay, so now that those
were lying, they now get put to death because they were trying
to kill the witnesses and they pay, hopefully before they die, the
husband 100 שקל. shekel. Okay, and we don't say it's קים ליה
kim lei because of what? Because ממון לזה ונפשות לזה. mammon le'zeh
u'nefashos le'zeh. We separate the court cases. Like similar to the discussion
before of separating a case of three and a case of 23.
So the crime against the witnesses, they were
עדים זוממים eidim zomemim and they have to get put to death.
The crime against the husband, they were עדים זוממים eidim zomemim and
they pay 100 שקל. shekel. And those are two separate crimes, even
though done in the same act, and therefore it is not a
case of קים ליה. kim lei. Each one is adjudicated separately and
they both will have to owe the husband, they or their estate,
and they will also be put to death.
So now you've got this double עדים... eidim...